hip dips also known as hip divots hip
dents and violin hips these are all
terms that are used to describe the
indentation that tends to form in
women's hips when you hear this term
it's usually a bad thing you know it's
used in a negative context you might
have even come across influencers who
tell you I'm going to do a hip dip
workout I'm going to show you how to get
rid of your hip dips in this video I'm
going to teach you why hip dips are a
natural process of getting stronger
leaner and more athletic why we should
normalize them and why there's no
special hip dip workout that's going to
cause you to eliminate your hip
[Music]
dips hip dips take one all right first
things first what is a hip dip as you
can see in the image below it's a
natural tendency for an indentation to
form in women's hips now you you'll see
this in untrained women but you also see
it in highly trained women in fact the
more muscle you build and the leaner you
get the more certain it is that you are
actually going to form hip dips why
because fat can cushion and round out
the area when you lean out and build
gluteal muscle it just makes it more
prominent it's an anatomical certainty
that you will develop hip dips if you
get strong enough and lean enough it
happens to everyone who gets really
really lean now it is more prominent in
some IND individuals compared to others
due to skeletal Anatomy some people just
have a natural hip and pelvic Anatomy
such that you can look at their you know
kind of the iliac crest and the greater
trochanter of the femur and there's not
a lot of space between those two points
all right whereas other people have much
more space and therefore much more room
to form a divot so there is a genetic
skeletal element to hip dips that that
is just genetic it's inherited you can't
do anything about it there's also gen IC
elment to muscular attachment points if
your skeletal structure where the
muscles attached happen to form in such
a way that really highlights that area
or creates those divots then yeah you're
going to have then you have a greater
propensity to have hip dips than someone
else but leaving genetics out of it
again most people do develop some degree
of hip dips if they get lean enough so
here's the deal I'm the glute guy people
come to me they want glutes they want
lower glutes they want upper glutes it's
hard because you know a lot of people
want that upside down heart shape you
know they want the glutes that have the
upside down heart shape but then from
the side view they want the Shelf they
want that rounded out you know
especially the upper portion and those
two things kind of conflict with one
another so I will say before I came
around there were more heart-shaped
glutes why because people only did axial
hip extension exercises back then in
other words people did solely vertical
hip extension exercises for their glute
training programs you know they did
lunges they did squats they might have
done step UPS or curtsy lunges so some
even did Romanian deadlifts but it was
all vertical in nature meaning you put a
bar on your back or a bar on your hands
or dumbbells in your hands and you Carri
it out hip extension and that tends to
work mostly the lower glutes it tends to
develop the lower glutitis Maximus well
so you did see that upside down
heart-shaped glute appearance the
problem was glutes weren't that big back
then seeing big strong muscular glutes
was very rare why because vertical hip
extension exercises are not the best
glute exercises horizontal hip extension
exercises are so when hip thrust and
glute brid
variations and even back extension
variations became more popular glute
development skyrocketed so over the last
15 years since hip thrusts have been
around you now see way bigger glutes
than you did before also the seated hip
abduction machines have become more
popular as well as booty bands you know
Mark Bell created The Hip Circle then I
started making the glute Loop and that
opened up the floodgates and now every
influencer has their own booty bands so
everyone's doing these booty band
workouts and they're doing their
abduction exercises and abduction
exercises tend to focus on the you know
upper subdivision of the glute Max and
the glute Medias so that upper glute
development is great when looking from
the side view for that shelf however
when looking from straight on either
from the front or from the back that's
where you tend to get this butterfly
shaped glute appearance you might not
have the upside down heart-shaped glutes
but from the side view you're going to
have that curve and let's say you're a
mere mortal and you don't have amazing
glute genetics then your only chance at
developing decent glutes is to be
performing all of the different glute
exercises please see my video on the
rule of thirds to see how you should be
optimally training your glutes so now
all these different glute exercises are
popular women are developing much bigger
glutes they've got the upper glutes
they've got the lower glutes and they
tend to get leaner over time they're
working out they're eating their protein
they're training hard they're building
glutes but they're leaning out take a
look at the glute Anatomy here how can
you get muscular impressive glutes
without having that divot it's
impossible that's just how the anatomy
looks a strong muscular well-developed
set of glutes has to have that divot
that's Anatomy you might be wondering
what about men why don't men get hip
dips well check out these male
bodybuilders here's Ronnie Coleman for
example as you can see he's got that
same butterfly shaped glutes the thing
is they have these huge quads you know
they vastest lateralis their thigh sweep
is so big that it kind of hides it you
don't even notice the hip dips you don't
notice that butterfly shaped glutes
because there's these huge thighs
covering it up in women you don't tend
to see the thighs like that especially
in like the bikini subdivision there's
body builder Phil Heath same thing you
see these hip dips all right what about
the current Mr Olympia big Remy again he
has hip dip look at this massive hollow
out area you see here so in men it's not
a big deal because of these huge thighs
that covered up with women it doesn't
have to we don't have to think it looks
weird I've seen so much of it I think
that it looks normal you know we can
think of it as looking athletic or even
sexy we need to normalize it check out
my client Rihanna Alexander check out
when she gets to the top here she is on
the pit shark now look at her glutes as
she locks out as she squeezes her glutes
you notice those hip dips up here so I
see that all day long as a trainer they
better be squeezing hard at the top of
their hip thrust their Kickbacks their
back extensions so I'm seeing this all
day long with all my clients that's why
when hip tips became a thing I was
really confused I'm like huh this is
normal this is natural and why would you
want to get rid of it now check out my
client Masa act Berry Mar she's known
for having very little hip dips you know
look at her posing check her out on
stage here I'm going to show you a bunch
of different pictures of her and you're
going to be like wow she does not have
any hip dips well that's because she's
mastered the art of posing now check her
out when I make her do a standing glute
squeeze as you can see she has hip dips
she's just good at hiding them so that's
case in point every woman when get
really strong lean glutes has them and
if she stands from the front you can
still see it so ladies don't be fooled
by pictures you see most of these women
have just mastered the art of posing and
they hide it but they definitely have
them especially when they do the
staining glue squeeze or when they're
performing any exercise that requires an
inrange hip extension squeeze
theoretically let's talk about how would
you solve this if you could what would
you do say don't do any more abduction
because abduction works the upper glutes
so say you atrophy the upper glute
region so now the hip dips aren't as
prominent but you don't have that shelf
when standing from the side the Shelf is
very coveted so if you had that you
wanted to lose you have to lose that
from all over you can't be like I'm
going to do an exercise that works this
area and I'm going to lose fat in that
area but regardless hip tips tend to
surface when you get too lean not when
you're a little bit heavier you know the
fat tends to hide it a little bit so
there's no fat burning methods you can
use and there's not really any good
muscle building methods you can use
because when you train the glutes
optimally you're going to develop all
the glute regions which means the
different subdivisions of the glutitis
medius the glutitis Minimus and the
glutitis Maximus and you're going to get
that butterfly look and finally
atrophying certain areas isn't a good
call because it might cause you to look
better from one angle but not a
different angle my guess is that you
would miss having the glutes if you let
them atrophy away so my advice normalize
hip dips if you have them be proud of
them know that they're a byproduct of
strong well-developed well-trained
glutes but if you are very insecure
about them try to learn posing
techniques so that when when you're
posing when you're taking pictures you
don't draw as much attention to that
area they're posing techniques that can
minimize the appearance of hip dips and
that mainly involves arching and kind of
tensing up but not too much you're
definitely not going to do a full-on
standing glute squeeze when you're
posing for a pick so that's my take on
hip dips I hope this video taught you a
thing or two I hope it caused you to
become more comfortable with your hip
dips and more willing to just train the
glutes as hard as possible and let the
chips fall where they may because it's
fun to be strong and not have to worry
about should I not push it so hard on
this exercise or should I quit doing
this movement okay that's a wrap please
make sure to like this video go ahead
and leave a comment if you're unsure
about hip dips and you want some
clarification definitely leave me a
comment and last but not least make sure
you're subscribed thank you for watching
what